hi Dean it's been a long time I finally
have a few new things to say at least
two I'll start with this one and I will
leave it to you to decide why it is that
this seems like something to say in the
context of the other things that I've
talked about so the notion here is
something called C Gnaeus the the the
concept was first introduced at least to
me by German name Brian Eno and he was
endeavoring to name the the fact that
there seemed to be a certain genius of a
scene where some kind of scene would
emerge say like punk rock or
skateboarding or Impressionism or
quantum mechanics where while the
individual participants themselves may
in fact also be geniuses there's
something about them together or the
emergence of the movement that seemed to
have its own independent genius and so
he calling that acini as' and friend of
mine gentleman named Sebastian Paquette
was very interested in this concept and
he and I talked about it quite a bit
while ago actually but eight years ago
it seems like and I was recently having
a conversation with Tim Kelly and she
recommended that I document the way that
seven I were thinking about it so so
this is it basically this is an
expansion you may call it the Macau how
did it seems roll out because it seems
that there's something characteristic
about scenes so to begin with a scene is
very it begins very vague it begins as a
feeling but does not have any voice it
cannot be said it cannot be seen it does
not have any symbolic characteristics
that are easily shared but he's a sense
almost a yearning of something that
wants to be and in the beginning there
will only be a very small number
of people who are uniquely attuned to
the scene so as to be able to feel it
enough has to be able to and attracted
to realizing it in some fashion so let's
just use I say Impressionism as an
example so you have your your Monet and
and there's some some feeling in Monet
that is orienting him and drawing him
towards changing art from
representational art to use something
else it has no name to it it's not clear
what it is there's no technique or
framework but there's a sense of what is
more right in this in this direction and
by doing this by acting on this feeling
he makes it more real he makes it more
concrete someone else who may not be
able to be as attuned as he is is able
to see water lilies and is able to say
hmm
there's something there that is now more
clear to me all right so you have a
progressive development you have a
development of the vague and potentially
very powerful sense of something that
wants to be and then there's a people
who are somehow uniquely attuned to this
thing that wants to be and some of whom
then choose to an endeavor to realize
the endeavor to actualize it and in
their actualization they make it more
legible they make it more perceivable
they make it more real now I would
propose that there seem to be three core
call it functions in this first
realization now these are functions
meaning that a given person may play all
three functions or two or just one and
certain people may may play these
functions at different points in time it
is the impossible in principle that it
may in fact take a whole group of people
to play a given function so so one
function I will call source source is
the most in alignment with the essence
of the sea so an individualist if except
what particular individual happens to
play the role of source this individual
is the the expressor or the actual Iser
of the scene whose expressions in actual
actualizations are most fully of the
essence of what the scene actually is
I'll get back to this source in a second
the other two I call the charismatic and
the artist the artist plays the role of
making the scene legible to itself the
artist is kind of developing the palette
of expressions that are signature
characteristics of what the scene really
is say for example you know the the use
of color and light and Impressionism as
part of the artistry of the palette of
what it is to be in an impressionist
painting would say in skateboarding in
the skateboarding scene it is perhaps
the the innovation of the ollie is a
expansion of the expressive palate of
the scene itself so the symbolic
language or the pattern language in its
increasing a spring expressivity is the
domain of artistry the charismatic is
the function that converts the scene
while still being in alignment with this
essence our so this is still playing a
role very close to source but converts
the scene into expressions to have
legibility to the rest of the world all
right so this is kind of what makes the
scene cool or desirable or sexy or
interesting you know this might be for
example wearing a leather jacket the
studded leather jacket oh with a safety
pin through your nose I believe or your
ear I can remote it was an early Punk
there's not necessarily part of the the
intrinsic palette of Punk to dress Punk
but it is the characteristic that gives
rise to the expression of punk in a way
that makes it legible to the rest of the
world that helps you know what Punk is
and by the way it also makes Punk
attractive to at least those aspects of
the rest of the world who are attracted
to the source right because it is still
source it is the thing it is expressing
itself honestly in a truly end with
integrity outside so artistry is about
creating the language inside it becomes
increasingly capable of expressing the
thing for itself and charisma is
creating the aesthetic for expressing it
outside and by the way also inside so so
these are the three now one of the
things that often is the case is that
we're looking at the history of a scene
the source is really only known to those
people who are keenly interested in the
scene
well right I knew her before the scene
got cool this is the kind of the Velvet
Underground or the Pixies it's I don't
know Drock perhaps I mean it's the
schrodinger everybody knows who shorter
is maybe only like physics quantum
mechanic groupies know about Dirac but
the idea is that the the source is held
in very high esteem because the source
is so close and so pure in the essence
of what the scene is but because they
are not necessarily participating in
artistry or charisma they are not as
legible in the broader environment okay
and so then these three functions and
again by the way one person can play all
three functions and the functions may
move you may say that John Lennon may
have been playing the role of artists
and charismatic and then sometimes maybe
more source and you know Paul McCartney
may been playing more of the role of
charismatic for example they've been
moving through time and space but as
these these functions begin to be
embodied and begin to be played out the
the scene becomes more real it becomes
more legible from the outside it becomes
more capable of people who are attuned
to it to become more
love sensing how they can act in the
context of it and and as a consequence
more people begin to participate which
means that you have more reality
associated with the nature of the scene
and now at a certain critical threshold
new kinds of functions begin to emerge
there for example the function of the
journalist the journalist it plays the
role of communicating the scene to the
outside world world you also have the
maid of the librarian or the archivist
who was doing the same thing internally
like the naming of the scene who named
it the scene who gives the scene its
names who gives the scene its final
signature symbols that stick and become
identified with it remember web 2.0 or
social networking or the internet right
the internet as a scene wasn't called
the internet originally there were
dozens of names that were played with
and somebody named it the internet and
that stock right so there's a there's an
enumeration there's a building out of a
of an increasingly formal vocabulary and
then there's a identification all right
there's a notion of being able to
identify who is in the scene this is a
the role Rolling Stone magazine
beginning the process of helping the
emergent rock and roll scene to get a
sense of who is who and what those
relationships are and what is happening
and where is what right there's a
mapping and a making visible who and
there are now enthusiasts there are fans
of the scene these are people who are
participating through charisma through
artistry through source but are not
necessarily generative of the unfurling
of the scene it is farthest horizons if
you can imagine the scene is kind of
like having a plane
and there's a circle that starts out
very very small no circles expanding and
the interior or 'ti of that circle is
the reasonably actualized scene so in
skating for example this is not just the
skate punks who begin to adapt the
charisma min the UN to dress like escape
skaters which didn't it it's important
at a certain point that didn't make any
sense than that at a certain point you
started to get a sense of what the
aesthetic of skating was and they began
to then practice the moves and maybe
they don't innovate anything they're
just playing with it and therefore
center the fans of the enthusiastic
participants but they're not posers
they're really skate punks they really
are connected to source and endeavoring
to participate in the scene for its own
purposes and of course are giving energy
to it they're buying skateboards they're
buying the clothes and accoutrements
that are associated with skateboard and
that energy is then flowing into the
scene which of course then gives rise to
the emergence of the next layer out
you've got your more parasitic artifacts
you've got your marketers you've got
your promoters you have your in fact
posers posers are very important posters
are people who can simulate the scene
they can participate usually through
charisma but not necessarily because
artistry requires a different kind of
skillfulness they look and talk and
sound like central members of the scene
but they are participating in that
energy principally from an orientation
towards their ability to move the energy
that should otherwise be going to the
maintenance of the scene to themselves
right they are in fact quite
significantly parasitic well obviously
we see this happening you say for
example in the blockchains scene they
got overrun by parasites pretty quickly
because they didn't have very much of an
immune system marketers and promoters
are less directly parasitic a marketer
begins the process of kind of playing
the the role of charisma or the role of
journalists even more thoroughly focused
on the conversion of the essence of the
scene into artifacts that are legible to
the outside world for the purposes of
exchanging scene for energy whatever
that energy
happens to be and the promoter is kind
of doing the same thing in the opposite
direction creating attraction to pull
people into the scene again for the
purposes of exchanging scene for energy
but also bringing people into the scene
which of course begins to dilute the
scene because the scene becomes more and
more about the effect unless and less
about this source now different scenes
have different immune systems different
scenes have different characteristics of
their ability to expand Punk for example
has a strong or had a strong immune
system it was relatively not able to be
marketed relatively not able to be
promoted but also therefore as a partial
consequence of that had a relatively
limited potential limited sphere of of
capacity by contrast the personal
computer scene and remember that that
was a scene there was a point in time
where there is a bunch of sort of weird
folks hanging around in dimly lit rooms
with card tables futzing around with
hardware and software on their own who
eventually gave rise to the articulation
of the scene itself and in the same
group and you know kind of went through
the same basic arc you've got your Steve
Jobs and your Wozniacki you've got the
the building out of the the librarian
function and the journalists function
you've got say the emergence of Wired
magazine that began the process of
promoting and extolling and expanding
I'm not moving from PC to Internet but
you kind of get the story the source the
essence of the scene in ways that were
increasingly legible and increasingly
attracted people into the scene and this
particular scene because of its
characteristics was simultaneously very
heavily parasitized but also had
extremely large sphere of capacity right
and in fact it just became part of world
it didn't it wasn't killed or it wasn't
completely decimated by the amount of
parasitism that settled on top of it you
know blocky and it remains to be seen
the swarming of the parasites was super
fast and really hard and so it may be
that the energy invite energy here I
mean both a human creativity and money
and other things the energy that was
necessary to maintain that scene it
allowed to develop on its own terms from
its source may have been prematurely and
massively redirected to these parasites
and the poor thing just sort of died in
the cradle or it may be that the
parasites did not kill it and it still
has enough vitality to grow and perhaps
it can even build an immune system to be
able to separate out the the posers and
to down-regulate the marketers to the
point where they're only focused on
their their marketing function is still
in alignment with the essence of the
scene in maintaining its homeostatic
integrity I think that's that